How's it going guys? Welcome back to another advanced tutorial. Uh,
this is part seven and this is all about staying organized. Um,
I had mentioned in the previous tutorial how how important it is to organize all
of your assets, but this is gonna show you exactly how I do it. And, um,
I think this is an effective way to be on top of your stuff. So,
organization requires energy upfront,
but ultimately creates efficiency for the future. Uh, you know,
there isn't a time investment required to get organized first,
then, you know, begin your process. But I guarantee you, when you start,
when you start the project organized, you're gonna,
you're gonna be able to get things done faster,
and you can also go back to it later on without any complications.
'cause when you just throw things together, it is so easy to get lost. Uh,
especially when you hand work over to another person or another editor,
they're gonna get lost too. So, uh, I know it's not perfect.
There's no perfect system to it 'cause um, there's so many moving parts,
but as an editor, uh, we should, we should be working towards that efficiency.
So the three goals of organization is easy access. All right?
No wasted searching.
How many times have you gone through your hard drive or Google Drive or
whatever, drive and try to find a file and you didn't know what you named it?
And it just repeats that process over and over and over again.
And that is just insanity. Okay? I hate doing that. I hate digging.
So you want to have everything in a located place where you remember how to do
it, and you also can call upon it again. Number two,
to be able to reuse and repurpose things. This is so important,
especially today. You want to maximize your content.
And if you know where it's at and you know, uh,
what it's titled and you know how to use it,
you can repurpose it and reuse it in other pieces of content.
So it doesn't just go to waste and it just doesn't die in a hard drive,
or it doesn't die on Google Drive somewhere. Um, you know,
and if you know it exists, um, somebody will use it. So number three,
it creates systems for sharing and scaling. This is also very important.
If you have a bigger team, you work with other team members.
If you wanna do collaborations, you wanna,
multiple people are editing one single file.
Like you gotta be organized there because other people may be more organized
than you or less organized. And however way you pass it on,
you just wanna make sure there's a system, all right?
And it's like just being courteous, especially being courteous.
Like you don't wanna just like drop a bunch of clothes in front of someone and
be like, here you go. Like, when you have it neatly organized and, and,
and maybe organized by different shirt type or color even, gosh,
does that make your life easier for the next person, right? Versus like, okay,
now, well, I have to do it. So that's just a courteous thing.
So there's a four different areas to organize.
You have your folders on your computer. You have the assets themselves,
you have the, the file names, okay? And you have your premier project.
All right? So let's break these down really quick. Let's break down the folders.
So our typical folder structure, and this could be different for everyone.
All right? I just wanna preface that you can have your own folder structure.
This is not one to copy 100%. If it doesn't work for you, totally fine.
But here's what we use. So we have our main folder,
we have our raws, we have our export, which is like the final video,
and then we have our references folder,
which is all of your premier project folders. Okay? So under here,
we have a lot of subfolders. Under export, we have sub-folders.
Everything we have here, we have subfolders, but these are three main folders.
Okay? So the main folder, this looks like this, if you, you know,
if you have a pc, it might look a little differently, but we, I use Mac.
So you know, you have your Export Raw Ref. And then under our raws,
we have these typical categories, animations, B-roll, brand assets, hooks,
modular clips, photography.
Remember the modular categories we had.
That's basically where all of this will go.
And because we work on a per project basis where we have lots of different
clients, we will, um, these main folders will be like the client's name, right?
Or the project name. So we, we follow this same structure each and every time.
So it's worth having, uh, creating these, these folders ahead of time.
And then just copying and pasting them into a new, uh,
anytime a new project comes up.
Here is what the export folder looks like. And this is what,
so we have like asset number 1, 2, 3, 4.
And then we have our references file where this is like the file that we would
share with any other editor if they wanted to go in the project and,
you know, re-edit it, you know, all of the assets, the graphics, the music,
the sound effects, the stock, the,
the visual effects would all be within these folders.
So it's not just cluttered into one, one folder. And you know,
it doesn't happen every single time in that perfect way. But ideally,
this is what we want. We want the consistency, we want the organization,
it's gonna make our lives easier, especially, you know,
if you're gonna link assets, you don't know where it is, it's just extra work,
and it's unnecessary. It takes up time. I hate it.
Okay, so next area to organize is your assets themselves.
Okay? So this is a shoot that we recently did was for Ella Oil. Ella Oola,
and I had mentioned this brand in a previous module,
but this is what it looks like, you know, before organization,
I just dumped everything into a folder. Now, when this happens,
like sometimes I'm in a rush and I'll just dump everything and then hand it off
to an editor with this.
But it causes a ton of confusion if you weren't there on the shoot, right?
So as an editor, if you just got this huge thing,
it would be very hard to be like, okay, what's going on here?
You would have to watch every single clip to know what everything is and what,
what video it belongs to. So what you want to do, um,
if you're responsible for shooting, uh, well, maybe if you're not,
this is editor of course, but just as a rule of thumb,
even if you are an editor and you got something like this, you're gonna want to,
um, you're gonna want to organize it in these types of folders, right?
So going through them and be like, okay, this is a hook, this is application.
This is a huge, this is a dropper. These are photos. So what I'm doing here,
I'm basically just, um,
taking what I see and creating a sub folder for it, you know, and I'm,
I'm finding the pattern of shots and I'm creating a group from it.
And I think this is very valuable because, um,
you'll see similarities in the shots,
and it's nice to just group 'em all together.
Especially when you're editing them. It's like, okay,
I know where all my dropper shots are, I know where all my pregnant shots are,
I know where all my application shots are, I know where, you know,
and the list goes on and on because like, if they're not all in one place,
you could miss, uh, an opportunity to review a shot that, you know,
was maybe a good shot that, um, you could use in the video. So,
you know, going from, let's see,
from this, this is a lot more manageable as, um, you know,
when you're, when you're in the timeline. So you can just drop,
drag and drop this entire thing into your timeline,
and you already have some sort of organization happening right now,
you can take it to a next level,
and you can actually organize the file names themselves,
depending on how much time you have and how much focus you have. Um,
if you're a d d like me, sometimes actually, you know, I enjoy it.
It's just that I have kids. So it's hard to name the files every time.
But ideally, in a perfect world, I would be.
So this is an example of, uh, a project where we did the file naming.
And remember, when it comes to file naming,
it doesn't have to be this perfect wild system that you have each,
every and every time. What, what, although it can be, um,
this is primarily for your own organization.
If you are editing the video or someone else is editing the video,
naming the files beforehand, before,
like you wanna name the files before it gets into Premier, okay?
Because when you, when you rename them in premier,
it doesn't rename the actual raw file. And it's kind of like, you know,
double work to have to do it, um, both times. So when you drag,
when you rename a file and you bring it into premier,
whatever software you're using, it's already named that file.
So it actually adds an additional layer of,
of categorization and organization for you. And what I do is just,
you know, a feature action, and then the version just simple, simple like that.
So it's like, okay, this is the back zipper moving up version one.
You know, especially if there's multiple shots, I'll just do like V one, V two,
V three, just to keep it really simple for me. Um,
this makes a huge difference in my timeline, um,
in my ability to sort and filter through good shots and ones that I don't need.
So I definitely recommend doing this. Like I said,
it takes a lot of energy upfront to do this,
but ultimately will make you more efficient in the long run. Okay?
Okay, so here is an example of modular clip naming,
and there is a tutorial on how to create modular clips. Um,
but basically this one is more, I would say more detailed,
but you can still follow similar structured.
So the whole point of modular clip, uh,
creating modular clips is finding the key points in your video,
which are actually usable,
and then creating little individual clips out of them so that they're drag and
drop onto your timeline.
And you don't have to do any scrubbing or anything additional to, um,
to the video. So this is an example of what that looks like. And, um,
without going too much in the detail of how to do this,
because there is a tutorial and how to do it, um, this is an example. It's like,
it's very easy for me as an editor to be like, all right,
I need some pain point shots. I need, um, you know,
blood or whatever the case may be. This is just descriptive, right? Um,
versus like the M 1, 4, 5, 9, MP four, like, I don't know what that is.
I don't know what that means. So, um, just another layer of organization,
it just helps you as an editor,
makes it more clear and makes you more effective. Alright,
the next place to organize is obviously your premier project.
So let's have a look at that. This is how we do it.
We have our raw, our sequence, our music, sound effects,
stock graphics and visual effects. If you're an editor,
you probably already know what these mean, but, um,
every project should start like this. That way, you know,
you don't have to recreate these every time. Uh, you got your raw,
your raw footage, your sequences, you know, pretty straightforward stuff here.
Um, graphics could be your brand assets and you can obviously add to this too,
if there's anything additional you want. But keeping everything in their,
in their parent folders is really important.
So you don't have everything just dragging into the main folder.
I know it's tempting to do that and sometimes I do it myself,
but I like to go back and then put everything into their respective folder.
Again, if you're sharing this, this project with someone else,
it's gonna make such a huge difference for them.
'cause everything's gonna be in one place, uh,
and they're not gonna have to try so hard to link everything and it just looks
nicer, man. It's just cleaner. And, um, I'm all about that.
So if you're not organized, this might be a challenge for you,
but it'll save you a lot of time and headache.
So the file and folder structure can vary from project to project.
Create your own naming conventions and structures that best suit your project.
Like I said, you can take mine, go for it. You can, uh, apply your own.
There's no perfect way or ride or wrong way to do it.
Whatever makes sense and works for you really, because I don't,
I know some people might have better systems. I don't care, or like,
not that I don't care, it's just like, go for it. You know? If it works,
it works.